Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is Chaf
Tet כט, Chaf Tet, 29, and the last daf דף daf of
the third perek פרק. perek. So we pick up just a little
bit behind about on Chaf Chet Amud Bet כח עמוד ב. Chaf
Chet Amud Bet.
Amar Shmuel אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, it's about ten lines before the
lines get wide. Line starts with the word, actually no, the line
before that, Ve'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Ve'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, so it starts with the word Yehuda
יהודה Yehuda there. So let me just say one thing. We have
been discussing what? Those three? I'm sorry? Yes. Hud shetzalvo bo basar
חוד שצלו בו בשר, Hud shetzalvo bo basar, you have that?
What? Yes.
Lo tzericha לא צריכא.
Lo tzericha. Right. Well, that's the line above it. I mean, yes,
that's the line, then it's Amar Rav Yehuda אמר רב יהודה. Amar
Rav Yehuda. Yes. So,
let me just wrap up what we said yesterday because it's a
very important discussion. We had the whole issue about Rabbi Yehuda רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, not Rav Yehuda רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, Rabbi Yehuda
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who's of the position that not only can
you do things that are directly involved in the food preparation, like
making the fire and cooking, but you can even do machshirei ochel
nefesh מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, things that are preparatory, which
would basically mean like one stage removed, particularly here the issue about
sharpening knives and doing, you know, fixing an oven, doing things
that are preparatory to the food preparation and not directly part of
it. And even machshirei ochel nefesh מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh
he allows,
as long as it was ee efshar la'asoso me'od yom אי אפשר
לעשותו מאוד יום, ee efshar la'asoso me'od yom, you could not do
it the day before, which is an interesting criteria, something we normally
expect on a derabbanan דרבנן, derabbanan, but here it sounds like de'oraita
דאורייתא. de'oraita. That de'oraita דאורייתא, de'oraita, if you could have done it
the day before because, meaning based on your time or when the
problem appeared and so on, then it is biblically forbidden to do
that on Yom Tov יום טוב, Yom Tov, but if you could
not have done it the day before, then it's biblically allowed. So
that is a very significant additional allowance in terms of things relating
to food preparation. Now, do we rule like Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? The upshot of the Gemara גמרא Gemara sounds very much
like we do rule like Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that
you are allowed to do machshirei ochel nefesh מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei
ochel nefesh that you were ee efshar la'asoso me'od yom אי אפשר
לעשותו מאוד יום. ee efshar la'asoso me'od yom. However, the Gemara גמרא
Gemara a little bit equivocates because of this idea of halacha ve'ein
morin ken הלכה ואין מורין כן, halacha ve'ein morin ken, that you
might not want to publicize this because it is very easy for
people to, once they allow, you allow this, they'll come to allow
cases even when it was possible to have taken care of it
the day before. But that's basically the principle of Rabbi Yehuda רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and that's basically the psak פסק psak of the
halacha הלכה halacha is that even machshirei מכשירי, machshirei, even machshirei ochel
nefesh מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, even preparatory things that you
could not have done the day before, you are allowed to do.
However, there's one important qualification, and that's what I wanted to end
with before we pick up with today's daf דף, daf, which is
that we had all this discussion in the Gemara גמרא Gemara about
sharpening knives, where sharpening knives is allowed, but you do it in
a slightly different way. You don't do it on the classical whetstone,
you do it on some other type of a thing, on a
basket, on wood, etc. But sharpening-wise is allowed, but fixing knives presumably
would be a problem. If it says if it's got, you know,
if it's really not able to cut at all and you make
it able to cut, then that would be a problem. So what
is that additional problem that's going on here? So Rashi רש"י Rashi
says, you know, to fix it from not being able to cut
at all to being able to cut is too much tircha טירחא,
tircha, too much effort, or maybe uvda de'chol עובדא דחול, uvda de'chol,
something of that nature. And that's why you need these shinuyim שינויים,
shinuyim, and that's why there are certain limits. But it's important to
note that the Ran ר"ן Ran and other Rishonim ראשונים Rishonim say
differently, and they say that even according to Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that you can do machshirei ochel nefesh מכשירי אוכל נפש,
machshirei ochel nefesh, you cannot do it to make a kli כלי
kli from scratch. You cannot basically say, oh, well, I don't have
any knives, let me go and I'll make molten, you know, metal
and I'll pour it into a mold and I'll make a knife
on Yom Tov יום טוב. Yom Tov. Like that you can't do.
You can fix something that's been dulled, but you cannot make something
what's considered to be making it from scratch. Even that Rabbi Yehuda
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would limit. And the cases here, like if
it can't cut at all or the cases of using a classical
whetstone or whatever, those would be cases which would get into the
category of being like making it from scratch, like making it and
not just fixing it. Now, why is that a problem? So what
the Ran ר"ן Ran explains is, he says it's similar to the
reason why you're not allowed to go out to your field and
harvest your wheat and grind your wheat and make flour. Right? Why
can't you do that? So remember we've discussed that. Why can't you
go and catch fish and hunt on Yom Tov יום טוב? Yom
Tov? And the basic answer is that things that are not immediately
in the context of the cooking, immediately in the context of, you
know, sort of getting it from the store and cooking it in
your kitchen, that are more long-term, you know, types of issues that
are not made in the immediate process of cooking, that is not
allowed. That's not in the context of ochel nefesh אוכל נפש. ochel
nefesh. So the same way you can't go harvest your wheat, you
can grind pepper but you can't grind wheat into flour because one
is in a context of cooking you do in the kitchen and
the other is in the context of something you do for large-scale
and long-term. So the same is true with your knife. If your
knife is dulled, you can sharpen it, but to take something that's
in the category of not being a knife anymore and make it
into a knife, well that’s like making things in the, you know,
in the factory, and that’s something that is not allowed. So bottom
line is, and that’s a very important distinction, that we basically rule
like רב יהודה Reb Yehuda that מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh
that you could not do the day before are allowed to be
done on יום טוב, Yom Tov, although there’s an issue about how
much you publicize that, הלכה ואין מורין כן, halacha ve’ein morin ken,
but it draws a line at basically like making a כלי kli
from scratch because that would sort of be like going out and
harvesting your wheat. So just to tell you a practical application of
that, which is the question about opening bottle caps. I don’t open
bottle caps on שבת Shabbos because, you know, I we won’t go
into the whole thing and I probably it’s probably a crazy חומרא
chumra at this stage based on what I now know about how
plastic bottle caps are made. Okay, but anyway, because there’s an opinion
that when you make the bottle cap and you break off the
ring that surrounds it, you’ve made it functionally into a כלי. kli.
Until that point, it could only keep the bottle sealed, but once
you break it off, you now make it functional in a new
way. Now it can go on and off of the bottle, and
it’s not just sort of keeping the bottle sealed and could be
used on other bottles that it couldn’t be before, fine. Do I
open bottles on יום טוב? Yom Tov? And the answer is yes,
but because you know, I mean you can cook on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, of course, you know, this חומרא chumra that I’ve got
is not opening bottle caps, so I’m gonna do it on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. It’s about, you know, being able to drink, and
it’s sort of it’s really like אי אפשר לעשות מביום i efshar
la’asos mi’be’yom because we all know that if you open the bottle
on ערב יום טוב erev yom tov the soda defizzes, right? Whatever.
So anyway, so the question is, so but I had this whole
quandary like why am I allowed to do that? Because if according
to if we are saying that making a כלי kli from scratch
is, you know, is something that even רב יהודה Reb Yehuda wouldn’t
allow, right, fixing a כלי kli yes, but making a כלי kli
no, well if I think it’s making a כלי, kli, I think
it’s making a כלי. kli. But I do think but I think
that, you know, in the end, the idea that the ר"ן Ran
speaks about about is this something that’s in the natural sort of
immediate sense of making the food and using the food and so
on or something that more is like long term, this might technically
be an עשיית כלי, asiyas kli, but it’s an עשיית כלי asiyas
kli that comes in the context of immediate access to the food.
So I don’t really think that it is, you know, that it
would fall into that problematic category even for those like myself that
are מחמיר machmir and don’t open bottle caps on שבת. Shabbos. Okay,
but that is an interesting issue
about מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh and not allowing really making
a כלי kli from scratch when it becomes completely non-functional and making
it functional, that would not be allowed. Let’s now pick up with
the wrap-up of this which gets us back to a מוקצה muktzeh
discussion. So, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, שפוד
שצלו בו בשר, shvut she’tzalu bo basar, if you have a spit
that was used to roast meat on יום טוב, Yom Tov, אסור
לטלטלו ביום טוב, assur letaltelo be’yom tov, you can no longer move
it on יום טוב Yom Tov because now it’s become disgusting, so
it’s like מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. muktzeh machmas miyus. So even though before
it wasn’t completely מוקצה, muktzeh, now you’ve made it completely disgusting and
it’s מוקצה. muktzeh. רב אדא בר אבא אמר רב מלכיו, Rav Adda
bar Abba amar Rav Malkio, שומטו ומניחו בקרן זוית. shomto u’minicho bekeren
zavit. What you’ll do is after you take the meat off, you
basically just
like push it off into a corner. רש"י Rashi says the word
שומטו shomto is like maybe you drag it, you don’t directly pick
it up with your hands, you kick it off into a corner.
ואמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב הונא, ve’amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Ashi amar Rav Huna, והוא
שיש עליו כזית בשר, ve’hu she’yesh alav kezayis basar, and even that
is only if there’s still a כזית kezayis worth, an olive’s worth
of meat on it, then it’s not completely מוקצה muktzeh because of
the meat that is still on it. Okay, if that’s true though,
you wonder why you have to, as רש"י Rashi says, kick it,
although again that aspect of kicking it is not explicit in the
גמרא. Gemara. רבינא Ravina אמר אף על פי שאין עליו בשר מותר
לטלטלו, amar af al pi she’ein alav basar muttar letaltelo, even if
it does have no meat on it you can move it. I
agree that it’s disgusting, but I’m still giving you an allowance to
move it. Why? מידי דהוה אקוץ ברשות הרבים, midei de’hava akotz bi’reshus
ha’rabim, like the same way that if you have a like a
dangerous shard, you know, like a nail, a rusty nail in רשות
הרבים, reshus ha’rabim, you’re allowed to pick it up and move it
so that people don’t get hurt by it. So here too, you
know, you have a spit that’s, you know, a sharp piece of
metal, you’re allowed to move it as well even if it doesn’t
have meat on it and even if it’s disgusting. Now you could
have also said that if it’s truly, truly disgusting, it has another
allowance. The other allowance of moving מוקצה muktzeh is something called גרף
של רעי, graf shel re’ee, which is basically like a bedpan, that,
you know, if you had the things which basically you, you know,
you use to go to the bathroom in, so that’s real מוקצה,
muktzeh, it’s real disgusting, on the other hand, what, we’re supposed to
leave it around the house and smell up the house on שבת
Shabbos and יום טוב? Yom Tov? So there was a specific allowance
to remove it. So the גמרא Gemara could have gone that direction
here as well, although maybe here it’s just looks disgusting but is
not actually smelly or something. All right. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי
אמר רב הונא, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav Huna, oh
we just did that. Okay. אמר רב חיננא בריה דרב איקא, amar
Rav Chinana brei de’Rav Ika, שפוד שפחות ובגומות shvut shfchos u’begumot רב
מלכיו. Rav Malkio. So this idea that you can kick it or
move it into a corner was said in the name of אמר
רב אדא בר אבא אמר רב מלכיו. amar Rav Adda bar Abba
amar Rav Malkio. So he said there are three teachings, basically there
are there’s a רב מלכיו Rav Malkio and a רב מלכיא. Rav
Malkia. Okay, and so easy names to get confused, and each of
them made sort of three comments on three different cases, and you'll
get confused
who said which three. So he's going to give you a little
way to remember which one said which of these three. So the
statements about the שפוד, shfud, about the spit, that if it's gotten
disgusting you can still move it to a corner,
that's רב מלכיא Rav Malkia as we said.
שפחות shifchos is a case about the משנה Mishnah discusses when a
woman gets married, based on how much property and slaves that she
brings into her marriage, what work she's expected to do around the
house. So there gets to be a stage where she has so
many maidservants that she doesn't have to do any work in the
house, and to which רב מלכיו Rav Malkio comments that we rule
like, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, even if she has
all these other maidservants to do work, she shouldn't do nothing because
to have no work to do, what is it, idle hands are
the devil's handiwork or whatever, it's not good to be completely to
have to do no work during the day. So and רב מלכיו
Rav Malkio says we rule like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So the
ruling like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in that משנה, Mishnah, that's רב
מלכיו. Rav Malkio.
שפוד שפחות, shfud shifchos, I lost my place again.
Oh, גומות. gumot. גומות gumot is a point about if you're looking
at pubic hairs, and the pubic hairs are supposed to grow from
like little indentations in the skin is where the hairs grow from,
and he says that if you see the indentations,
even if you don't see the pubic hairs, you can assume that
the pubic hairs were there in terms of determining if somebody is
an adult or not, okay, a young boy or girl. So those
three statements were said in the name of רב מלכיו. Rav Malkio.
בלורית, blorit, which now this is another series of statements. בלורית blorit
is a way of cutting hair that would be done
particularly in a pagan and עבודה זרה avodah zarah way, and there
was a discussion about when you get, so רב מלכיא Rav Malkia
says when you get within three fingerbreadths of where the hair would
be cut that way, you have to stop cutting. So that's בלורית.
blorit. אפר מקלה, efer mikleh, which is like ashes, burnt ashes, and
here's an issue about you're not allowed to put burnt ashes on
a wound because
it'll sort of stain the skin and it'll look like a tattooing.
And גבינה, gevinah, which is the question about why is it that
we're not allowed to eat the cheese made by non-Jews. And that
was רב מלכיא, Rav Malkia, so all of those were רב מלכיא.
Rav Malkia. רב מלכיא Rav Malkia explained them those three statements. Okay,
so now you know which three are רב מלכיו Rav Malkio and
which three are רב מלכיא. Rav Malkia. רב פפא Rav Papa אמר,
amar, מתניתין ומתנייתא matnisin umasniyasa רב מלכיו, Rav Malkio, no. Anything that
relates to a משנה Mishnah or
ברייתא, Braisa, explaining it or פוסק-ing paskin like a particular opinion, that's
רב מלכיו. Rav Malkio. שמעתתא, shmaytasa, anything that's an Amoraic statement, that's
רב מלכיא. Rav Malkia. Okay, now how do you remember that? וסימנך,
vsimanach, the way to remember it is מתניתין מלכותא, matnisin malchusa, the
Tannaitic statements, the משנה Mishnah and the ברייתות, Braisas, those are the
queens, those are more important, those are the heads, as opposed to
the Amoraic statements. Of course it's so funny, they're two names רב
מלכיא, Rav Malkia, רב מלכיו, Rav Malkio, how you're supposed to remember
that the משנה Mishnah is רב מלכיו, Rav Malkio, but anyway, I
guess מלכא malka like a queen and רב מלכיא, Rav Malkia, I
don't know. Anyway, מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, now what's the difference if
you split it up based on משנה Mishnah and ברייתא Braisa versus
Amoraic statement? איכא בינייהו שפחות, ika beinaihu shifchos, which one you sort
of attribute the case about the maidservants to, which switched based on
his organization of משנה Mishnah and ברייתא. Braisa. We won't work through
the details. Now you know who's רב מלכיו Rav Malkio and who's
רב מלכיא. Rav Malkia. Moving on. Okay, but that's the end of
the discussion about the issue about the spit, but as I said,
also the very important discussion of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position about
מכשירי אוכל נפש. machshirei ochel nefesh. Next משנה. Mishnah. לא יאמר אדם
לטבח. lo yomar adam letabach. Now we get back to purchasing, and
the rest of this פרק perek will be focused on exactly this
issue that we've introduced, which is ways of getting purchasing the foods
that you need on יום טוב Yom Tov if you did not
take care of it from before יום טוב, Yom Tov, but in
a way that's not a problem of עובדין דחול uvdin dechol or
too much of a sense of commerce and purchase. לא יאמר אדם
לטבח, lo yomar adam letabach, a person should not say to a
butcher, שקול לי בדינר בשר, shkol li bedinar basar, give me a
dollar's worth of meat, or ten dollars' worth of meat, you don't
pay him the money, but don't describe the amount of meat you
want in terms of how much it costs. That's too much like
purchase on יום טוב. Yom Tov. אבל שוחט ומחלק ביניהם, aval shochet
umachalek beineihem, he slaughters it and he gives you a portion and
you'll work it out afterwards. Now that's not so helpful. What do
you mean he gives a portion? How do you figure out how
much you're going to owe him? So that's what the גמרא Gemara
asks. היכי עביד, heichi avid, what do you do? כי הא דבסורא,
ki ha devesura, like in Sura, דף כט עמוד א, daf kaf
tes amud alef, אמרי תרמתא ופלגו תרמתא, amri tarmasa upalgu tarmasa, they
speak about a particular cut and they'll call it like the cut
of, רש"י Rashi says these are very well identified. by cuts of
the meat. It's interesting because I wonder if you could have said
that these are also like weights or sizes, but רש"י Rashi says
these are cuts of the meat like, you know, the like the
flank, you know,
or rib. So in סורא Sura they'll describe it as a תרמתא
tarta or a half a תרמתא. tarta. In נרש, Narsh, אמרי amri
חלקה ופלגו חלקה. chalka u-palgu chalka. The רש"י Rashi says this is
describing the same cut of meat. They'll call it like a חלק
chelek or half a חלק. chelek. בפומידיתא B'Pumbedita אמרי עוזיא ופלגו עוזיא
amri uzia u-palgu uzia or an עוזיא uzia or half an עוזיא.
uzia. That's what they call it in פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. בנהרדעא ובמתא מחסיא
B'Neharde'a u-ve-Mata Mechasya אמרי
ריבעא ופלגו ריבעא. amri riva u-palgu riva. So again these are different
ways of describing all the same thing. What is that thing? Again,
רש"י Rashi says we're talking about very specific types of cuts of
meat. And then afterwards, you'll figure out how much that cut of
meat, presumably also there's a predefined size, weight to that meat, like,
you know, which is why I thought that it maybe meant a
more of a more of a measure than of a cut. I
don't know, do they say in the שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz in the article
any other suggestion like whether it means, you know, whether these things
are weights or measures or whether they are actually רש"י Rashi says
it's like a cut, like a rib. Like a standard cut. A
standard cut. He just quotes רש"י. Rashi. Yeah, I don't know if
שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz does שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz quote anything interesting from the Aramaic or
any other possible read? Anyway, it's either a standard cut or it's
a standard size. So but you do not talk about give me
X amount dollars' worth of meat. Now we finish this up with
this next משנה, Mishna, which is similar type of a discussion. Okay,
and the next two משניות, Mishnayot, the rest of the פרק Perek
will be a similar discussion. אומר אדם לחבירו, Omer adam l'chaveiro, a
person can say to his friend—now you're not going to the storekeeper,
you're going to your friend—but you still want to, you know, when
you go to your friend and you say can I have like
a, you know, I need two eggs, so sometimes, you know, I
think most of us nowadays you give them two eggs you don't
expect to get it back, but you know, there are times when
people don't, you know, can't afford that. So sure, I'll be happy
to give you two eggs, but I'm expecting to get the eggs
back afterwards. So now you're going to your friend for some food
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but you're going to have to give
it back. How do you determine how much they've given you? So
two eggs is easy, but how about flour? So you say could
I have a cup of flour? Well, are you allowed to measure
a cup of flour? You're not allowed to measure on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, right? On שבת ויום טוב Shabbat v'Yom Tov you're not
allowed to do מדידה, medidah, measurement. Okay, and also a measurement in
general is forbidden even as measuring your own flour. And number two
is in getting it from your friend, does that also make it
too much again like a type of a מקח וממכר mekach u-memkar
when you're being very specific about the amount? So there's A, just
measurements in general and B, the transactionary nature of this. So let's
take a look. אומר אדם לחבירו, Omer adam l'chaveiro, you can say
to your friend, מלא לי כלי זה. Malei li k'li zeh. You
know, let me have a, let me have a, fill up for
me this vessel of flour on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and implicitly
I'll pay you back after יום טוב. Yom Tov. אבל לא במידה,
Aval lo b'midah, but you cannot have a specific quantity, meaning you
can't say I want a cup of flour but you can bring
over something and say fill this up for me. רבי יהודה אומר
אם היה כלי שמדה לא ימלאנו. Rabbi Yehuda omer, im hayah k'li
she-midah lo yiml'enu. If it was a vessel used for measurement, you
should not fill it up. Now that sounds exactly like what we
said a minute ago. So the גמרא Gemara will try to understand
what subtle difference there is between the first statement and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda's statement. מעשה באבא שאול בן בטנית, Ma'aseh b'Abba Shaul ben
Botnit, there's a story of אבא שאול בן בטנית Abba Shaul ben
Botnit שהיה ממלא מדותיו מערב יום טוב ונותנם ללקוחות ביום טוב. she-hayah
memalei midotav m'erev yom tov v'notnam l'lakuchot b'yom tov. So here, apparently
he wasn't just like a neighbor, he was actually a storekeeper. And
he would fill up, you know, a cup worth of flowers or
whatever it was, you know, a gallon gallons worth of wine or
whatever the measurement was before יום טוב, Yom Tov, so all the
measuring would be done before יום טוב. Yom Tov. And then somebody
came to the store and they wanted a bag of flour—he gave
them a cup, like, but it already had been pre-measured before יום
טוב. Yom Tov. Or he gave them a container of wine—well, bottle
of wine is too easy—but whatever, he gave them a container of
wine, but it'd already been pre-measured before יום טוב. Yom Tov. ונותנם
ללקוחות ביום טוב. V'notnam l'lakuchot b'yom tov. And then, you know, again,
they would pay back afterwards. אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, אבא
שאול Abba Shaul says, again, this presumably is different, not the אבא
שאול בן בטנית, Abba Shaul ben Botnit, אף במועד עושה
כן מפני בירורי מדות. af b'moed oseh kein mipnei beirurei midot. He
would do it even on חול המועד Chol HaMoed because that you
would pre-measure from the night before because of the בירורי מדות, beirurei
midot, which means sort of the
imprecision of the measuring because when you pour let's say wine, you
know, it bubbles and if you wait for it to settle you'll
get a much more precise measure. So he would measure from the
night before even if it wasn't יום טוב, Yom Tov, even on
חול המועד Chol HaMoed because he wants to make sure that he's
giving the people exactly the amount that they had asked for, so
he wanted to wait for it to settle. Now the question is
what does that have to do
with חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? So let's take which is the next
statement in the גמרא. Gemara. וחכמים אומרים אף בחול עושה כן מפני
מיצוי מדות. V'Chachamim omrim af b'chol oseh kein mipnei mitsui midot. And
חכמים Chachamim say even in a weekday you should measure things out
from the day before because of מיצוי מדות, mitsui midot, which is
a similar idea to בירורי מדות. beirurei midot. רש"י Rashi says the
difference is one is like I said if you're measuring let's say
wine there are like airs and bubbles and you want to wait
for it to settle, the other is if you're measuring oil So
it'll maybe you know you have your container has exactly the right
amount of oil in it. It's got whatever it is one what
would you say ounce or whatever of oil but then when you
want to pour it into the person who the other person's you
know vessel it's going to take like an hour for all of
the oil to come out. So he said what you should do
is the night before if you really want to be honest if
somebody's going to buy you know wants to buy from you a
cup of oil you say leave your vessel over and come back
tomorrow and pick it up and then you turn you know your
pre-measured amount in and you wait the whole night for it to
slowly drip out so you give him exactly what he was purchasing.
Okay now why exactly if those are the concerns of the last
two statements why exactly it mentions חול המועד Chol HaMoed is not
clear now but it'll be clarified in the גמרא. Gemara. Obviously then
it should be even in the weekday which is the last statement
so that'll be clarified in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look
in the גמרא. Gemara. מאי אבל לא במדה? Mai aval lo bemidah?
What is this debate between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says
you cannot borrow with measurement and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says if
it's a vessel used for measuring don't fill it? Sounds like the
exact same. So מאי אבל לא במדה Mai aval lo bemidah what
does it mean not to measure according to the תנא קמא? Tanna
Kamma? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel אבל
לא בכלי המיוחד למדה. aval lo be-kli ha-meyuchad le-midah. You can not
use a vessel that has been designated and has already been used
for measuring like a measuring cup. אבל כלי העומד למדה Aval kli
ha-omed le-midah but let's say it's a vessel that could become used
for that purpose. Like you have something that is you know exactly
the right size and if your current measuring cup breaks you'll have
this other vessel you'll use this as your new measuring cup but
you haven't used it for that yet. Okay and again it's not
like it's got you know marks along the edge so you know
it's already you know clearly a measuring cup. It's something that could
easily be used as that but has yet to be used for
that.
אבל כלי
העומד למדה ימלאנו. Aval kli ha-omed le-midah yimla'ennu. That you can do
if it hasn't yet been used for that purpose and it's not
yet identified as such. ואתא רבי יהודה ואמר Ve-ata Rebbe Yehuda ve-omer
and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is coming along and saying אפילו כלי
העומד למדה לא ימלאנו. afilu kli ha-omed le-midah lo yimla'ennu. You can't
even use a vessel that would eventually serve that purpose. That's already
too much like measuring and too much like a type of עובדא
דחול uvda de-chol especially maybe for yourself you can do it but
not when you're borrowing from your friend that's already too clearly defining
how much the exact amount that you're borrowing and that's too much
like business and transaction. Okay so that's the debate whether you can
use this vessel that has yet to be used for measuring but
that's how it can serve. אלמא Alma says the גמרא Gemara okay
if we frame it that way what would emerge is גבי שמחת
יום טוב gabei simchas Yom Tov regarding שמחת יום טוב simchas Yom
Tov now it's very nice the גמרא Gemara says this right all
along we've had all of these leniencies of ways you can buy
food on יום טוב Yom Tov without actually buying it as long
as you're sensitive to עובדא דחול uvda de-chol issues. And we've been
saying that it's an extension of the way the תורה Torah allows
אוכל נפש ochel nefesh allows you to do things relating to food
and cooking or whatever. The Rabbis also allow you to do a
certain amount of business you know purchasing relating to food as long
as you don't do it in a too blatant way and in
an עובדא דחול uvda de-chol way. So the גמרא Gemara here articulates
that allowance to do things related to cooking and food by the
words שמחת יום טוב. simchas Yom Tov. Which okay that's pretty obvious
but it's nice to have that type of identification that that's what
it's about why we want you to be able to cook. And
actually it's worth noting that רמבן Ramban says it's not incidental רמבן
Ramban says why is it that the תורה Torah gives you more
allowance on יום טוב Yom Tov than on שבת? Shabbos? Why are
you allowed to cook on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Why does the
תורה Torah allow you to do that? So maybe you could say
well you know שבת Shabbos is so holy you know it's whatever
it's מעשה בראשית ma'aseh bereishis and so on it has higher degree
of holiness and that means more things are forbidden. But the רמבן
Ramban says well actually the reason that the specific allowance on יום
טוב Yom Tov is around areas of cooking is because of שמחת
יום טוב. simchas Yom Tov. Since the idea of שמחה simcha is
central to יום טוב Yom Tov והיית אך שמח ve-hayisa ach sameach
right and that's not a central idea by שבת Shabbos so the
תורה Torah wants to make it
as possible
as you know give you as much opportunity to have that joy
which means making it easier for me to cook and prepare food
on יום טוב Yom Tov itself. So it's interesting to note that
that idea of שמחת יום טוב simchas Yom Tov as an allowance
for food preparation is what the רמבן Ramban says is behind why
the תורה Torah allows you to prepare food on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. And here the גמרא Gemara is using that phrase of שמחת
יום טוב simchas Yom Tov to explain why you're allowed to do
certain degree of purchasing of food. Okay so let's keep on going
but again so that's just key that the way the גמרא Gemara
frames it is by that word שמחת יום טוב. simchas Yom Tov.
אלמא Alma says the גמרא Gemara you see that גבי שמחת יום
טוב gabei simchas Yom Tov רבי יהודה לחומרא Rebbe Yehuda le-chumra רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda even though it's an issue of getting food on
יום טוב Yom Tov and a type of buying food and it's
about שמחת יום טוב simchas Yom Tov רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is
going to be a little bit stricter he won't let you use
a vessel even if it has yet to be used as a
measuring
vessel. רבי יהודה לחומרא Rebbe Yehuda le-chumra רבנן לקולא rabbanan le-kula the
Rabbis will be lenient. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute לאיפכא
שמעינן להו le-ipcha shaminan le-hu we just heard in an earlier... earlier
משנה Mishna, *Mishna* that the reverse. דתנן Detnan, *De-tnan*, the משנה Mishna,
*Mishna* teaches: רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר שוקל אדם בשר כנגד הכלי
או כנגד הקופיץ *Rebbi Yehuda omer shokel adam basar keneged ha-kli o
keneged ha-kupis*, that if you come to getting meat from the butcher,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* allows you to use the balance
scale if on the other side you don't put fixed weights but
you put like, you know, a hatchet or some other vessel. ורבנן
*Ve-Rabbanan*, the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* אומרים *omerim* אין משקילין בכף מאזנים כל
עיקר *ein mashkilin be-chaf moz-nayim kol ikkar*. You can't use the balance
at all. So there it's the opposite. Same type of a concern.
How can you get food on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*?
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* is more lenient, gives you
more latitude, and the Rabbis are more strict. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says אמר רבי יהודה לקולא ורבנן לחומרא Rabbi Yehuda le-kula ve-Rabbanan
le-chumra, *Amar Rebbi Yehuda le-kulla ve-Rabbanan le-chumra*. So there we see that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* was more lenient in terms of
getting food on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* and the Rabbis
were strict. קשיא דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה קשיא דרבנן אדרבנן Kashya de-Rabbi
Yehuda ad de-Rabbi Yehuda, kashya de-Rabbanan ad de-Rabbanan, *Kashya de-Rebbi Yehuda a-de-Rebbi
Yehuda kashya de-Rabbanan a-de-Rabbanan*. So it's a contradiction of both of their
positions. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אדרבי
יהודה לא קשיא *Rebbi Yehuda a-de-Rebbi Yehuda lo kashya*. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* is not contradicting himself. התם *Hasam*, over there when
it comes to using the balance scale בשאינו עומד למדה *be-she-eino omed
le-midda*. At the end of the day, if you're using a hatchet
on your balance scale, you're clear, that's something that clearly is never
used in the context of measuring. And therefore that makes that whole
transaction to be bizarre and not about a normal way of purchasing.
But the scale itself, okay, and the scale itself he would say
is, you know, counterbalanced, you know, is reframed by the use of
this vessel that is so bizarre. אבל הכא *Aval hacha*, but here
he says דעומד למדה *de-omed le-midda*. But here, the vessel is something
that is, that is, would normally be used. Maybe you haven't used
it yet, but it's the normal type of a vessel that would
be used when you measure and when you purchase. So there's nothing
sort of visual, you know, and obvious about the transaction here that
makes it look different from the normal way you would do a
transaction because you're using a type of a vessel that you would
normally use. There you're using a hatchet to weigh on a scale.
It's clearly a different type of a thing. So that's why he
could switch his position. דרבנן אדרבנן נמי לא קשיא De-Rabbanan ad de-Rabbanan
nami lo kashya, *De-Rabbanan a-de-Rabbanan nami lo kashya*. And the Rabbis and
the Rabbis are also not difficult. התם קעביד כעובדין דחול Hatam ka-avid
ke-uvdin de-chol, *Hasam ka-avid ke-uvdin de-chol*. There you are doing like you
do during the weekday. And רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, like you were
saying Dov, that you're using a, you're using a scale. The very
use of the scale makes it clear that this is an act
of measuring, whatever you put on the other side of the scale.
הכא לא קעביד כעובדין דחול Hacha lo ka-avid ke-uvdin de-chol, *Hacha lo
ka-avid ke-uvdin de-chol*. And here you're not doing it because you're not
using something. So on the one hand, you're using a hatchet there,
but you're also using a scale. And the scale is clearly earmarked
for, you know, business type of transaction purposes. It's a business object.
Whereas here you're using an object that has yet to be used
in the context of sale, you know, it's not yet been put
to that type of use. So therefore it is going to be
allowed. Which basically means, and it's an, it's an important point, you
know, we sometimes tend to oversimplify and say, oh, so-and-so is a
מיקל *meikel*, you know, he's very lenient, or this person is a
big מחמיר *machmir* in terms of פסק *psak*. But
you know, sometimes it's not about being מיקל *meikel* or being מחמיר
*machmir*. It's about the particulars of the case. I'll look at one
case and the specific particulars are going to tell me I don't
think you can do that on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*.
And I'll look at another, and it's all about, you know, buying
and going and getting something from the store. But the exact particulars
to me may seem like it's too weekday, makes it too much
like a weekday activity. Another case, I'll make a judgment that'll be
stricter than somebody else because in my judgment this other case makes
it too much like a weekday activity. Somebody else doesn't think that,
but I do think that. So you can really have different positions
on cases based on the circumstances, and they're not generally across the
board מיקל *meikel* or מחמיר *machmir*. Like some people think like the
חזון איש *Chazon Ish*, oh, he's a big מחמיר *machmir*, he's מחמיר
*machmir* in everything. I could show you dozens of cases where the
חזון איש *Chazon Ish* is מיקל *meikel* because that's just the way
he reads the סוגיא *sugya* and it comes up to a more
lenient position than other people read it, you know, but each case
deserves its own judgment. Yes.
I want to go back to that רמב"ן *Ramban* for a moment.
Is there a conceptual difference between שמחת יום טוב Yom Tov. *Simchat
Yom Tov* and עונג שבת Shabbat *Oneg Shabbat*?
Yes, so עונג *Oneg* is much more, it's a good point, you
know, עונג *Oneg*, first of all, first of all, עונג *Oneg* is
from the נביאים *Nevi'im*, it's not in the תורה *Torah*. Okay? So
obviously it wouldn't factor into have that same degree of weight. שמחה
*Simcha* is in the תורה *Torah*. עונג *Oneg* is more about physical
pleasure. שמחה *Simcha*, joy, is different. Like, you know, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* first says that the true שמחה *Simcha* is bringing קרבנות *korbanot*,
but it's a more, you know, a state of elation and, you
know, and it's not just the reality of pleasure. So, you know,
and that possibly is the issue here. I mean, why, why does
cooking on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* being more שמחה *Simcha*?
So it could just mean that the food is fresher. You don't
have to cook it before and then keep it on the warming
plate. You could, you know, eat fresher, and then you are right.
It's more of an issue of עונג *Oneg* than it is of
שמחה *Simcha*. It's more pleasurable. That's true. But it also could be
just giving me that allowance, that freedom, you know, to type of
cook or whatever, just makes the day more about enjoying myself and
more about like שמחה *Simcha* than it does about, you know, so
it does, it does more than just increase the sense, sensory, you
know, pleasure that's involved. But it's a good point, you know, that
עונג *Oneg* is also a relevant. In fact, factor to food; it's
a pretty directly relevant factor to food. Okay, so let's now continue.
Okay, so that's one way of reading it. Whether it's a vessel
that's been used for this purpose or not, and they might reverse
their positions or the leniencies and stringencies because of the specifics of
the case. רבא Rava אמר, רבא Rava says, מאי אבל לא
במידה, Mai aval lo be-midda, what does this mean in the משנה,
Mishna don't use it with measure? So רבא Rava says what I
think is probably an easier read of the משנה, Mishna שלא יזכור
לו שם מידה, she-lo yizkor lo shem midda, that
it's not talking about what vessel you're using. Don't go to your
friend and say, "Can I please have three ounces, a half a
cup of flour?" Don't explicitly mention the measure amount. Okay, like before
we said don't measure the money, to give me two dollars' worth
of meat; here, this would seem less of a problem, but don't
mention the exact measurement. Give me a half a cup of flour.
That's what the חכמים are saying. אבל כלי המיוחד למידה ימלאנו, Aval
kli ha-meyuchad le-midda yemalle'enu, but you could actually use a vessel that
is designated for—so I can go with my measuring cup right from
my kitchen, which clearly is a cup's worth of flour, right? And
I could go with, you know, or you know, one of those
individual things that's a cup, and I could say, "Could you please
fill this up for me?" That's okay. You could use a measuring
cup, but you can't say, "I need a cup of flour." Okay,
that's what רבא Rava says. In one way it's more obvious that
you are being precise and measuring than the other way. That's what
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says. אבל כלי המיוחד למידה ימלאנו. Aval
kli ha-meyuchad le-midda yemalle'enu. ואתא רבי יהודה ואמר, Ve-ata Rabbi Yehuda ve-omer,
and then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is going to be more strict
and he's saying כלי המיוחד למידה לא ימלאנו, kli ha-meyuchad le-midda lo
yemalle'enu, because this makes sense because רבי יהודה specifically emphasizes the vessel.
Don't fill up a measuring vessel. So for him, even if you
don't say, "I need a cup of flour", if you're bringing over
a measuring cup, then you can't fill it up. אלמא גבי שמחת
יום טוב, Alma gabei simchat Yom Tov, now the גמרא Gemara is
going to go through the exact same thing. Oh, now according to
your read, רבי יהודה is being strict, even though it's about enjoying
יום טוב, Yom Tov, getting food for יום טוב. Yom Tov רבי
יהודה לחומרא ורבנן לקולא, Rabbi Yehuda le-chumra ve-Rabbanan le-kula, because רבי יהודה
won't even allow you to use the measuring cup even without mentioning
the amount. והא איפכא שמעינן להו, Ve-ha ipcha sham'inan lehu, we heard
the opposite. דתנן, רבי יהודה אומר שוקל אדם בשר כנגד הכלי וכנגד
הקופיץ, Rabbi Yehuda omer shokel adam basar keneged ha-kli ve-keneged ha-kuppitz, you're
allowed to weigh meat on a scale against a vessel or against
some type of a hatchet. וחכמים אומרים אין משקילין בכף מאזנים כל
עיקר, Ve-Chachamim omerim ein mashkilin be-chaf moznayim kol ikkar, you can't use
the scale at all. אלמא, Alma, you see when it comes to
getting a hold of... to getting food for יום טוב, Yom Tov
רבי יהודה לקולא ורבנן לחומרא, רבי יהודה is lenient and the rabbis
are strict, the opposite of what you said here. קשיא דרבי יהודה
אדרבי יהודה קשיא דרבנן אדרבנן, so they're reversing... they're contradicting themselves in
one משנה mishna to the next. So the גמרא Gemara says, דרבי
יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא. De-Rabbi Yehuda ad de-Rabbi Yehuda lo kashya.
No, רבי יהודה is not contradicting himself, one case strict, one case
lenient. It's not a contradiction. התם בשאינו מיוחד למידה, Hatam be-she-eino meyuchad
le-midda, like we said before, when you use the hatchet on the
scale, you're using something that is never used in the context of
measuring, so therefore it clearly makes that a not normal transaction and
a non-business type of transaction. הכא מיוחד למידה, Hacha meyuchad le-midda, here,
even if you don't say a cup of flour, you're giving the
person a measuring cup, so it looks like a normal type of
a transaction. So here we're going to be more strict. דרבנן אדרבנן
נמי לא קשיא, and the rabbis go the reverse. התם קעביד כעובדין
דחול, there you're using a scale, which is very much a business
type of a, you know, of a... of an instrument, and therefore
it feels very much like a weekday activity. הכא לא קעביד כעובדין
דחול, here even though you're giving somebody your, you know, your measuring
cup, it doesn't make it look like this weekday business
activity. Why not? דעבידי אינשי דמקרבי חמרא במנא דכילא ושתו, De-avidi inishi
de-mekarvei chamra be-mana de-kila ve-shatu, people will bring over wine in a
measuring cup and they'll drink it. Like I know, you know, I
want to go over to your house and I want to bring
over some wine and we're going to drink together and I'll bring
it over not in a bottle, but I'll bring it over in
a vessel that I would normally use for measuring. Sometimes those things
do double duty, right? So since I sometimes will bring over something
just as a way of conveyance and I'll use a measuring cup
not necessarily as a way of measuring, but sometimes it'll do double
duty and I'll use it as a way of giving you something,
giving something to my friend. Here too, you come to my house,
you say you'd like some flour, I give you a flour... I...
you know, I scoop it up in a measuring cup and I
give it to you, it doesn't necessarily look like we're doing a
transaction. I gave you exactly a cup of flour and you're going
to owe me for it. Maybe it's just a vessel that I
used to give you something. Okay, but if I say, "Here's a
cup of flour", I explicitly label it, that makes it already look
like a transaction. Okay, so again, it's clear that the issue here
is we allow something that implicitly is going to be paid back
and is going to be purchased afterwards, but we can't too obviously
label it as a type of a transaction and business exchange on
יום טוב. Yom Tov And exactly the particulars, what will mean that,
is it used about explicitly labeling something, or visually something being different
and so on, that's somewhat of what's being debated between רבי יהודה
and the רבנן. Rabbanan. Let's take a look now at this other
issue, which gets us away from the יום טוב Yom Tov concerns.
מעשה באבא שאול בן בטנית. Ma'aseh be-Abba Shaul ben Botnit. So first
אבא שאול בן בטנית Abba Shaul ben Botnit would fill up his,
you know, his vessels of wine and oil, whatever, before יום טוב,
Yom Tov, as an exact measure. Somebody would come to borrow, he'd
give... on the vessel, you know, he'd know exactly how much without
necessarily doing any of the measuring on יום טוב Yom Tov, or
mentioning any names of measure, any names of measurement. תנא Tana so
the גמרא Gemara moves beyond that and gets to now the non-יום
טוב Yom Tov aspect. אף במועד עושה כן Af b'mo'ed oseh kein
he would even do this on the מועד Moed מפני ביטול בית
המדרש mipnei bittul Beis haMedrash because it would lead he didn't want
to be out of the בית המדרש. Beis Medrash. So on חול
המועד Chol haMoed he had more time to be sitting and learning
and other people had more time and they would be asking him
שאלות shailos and he wanted to be very free for people in
terms of learning so if people but he also had to run
a store you know like they tell the stories of like the
חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim right he had like this store so what
he would do is he wanted to have he would use nighttime
when people weren't asking him learning questions to get everything ready in
the store and to pre-fill up all the measurement so if anybody
wanted something he'd have it ready to give to them and he
wouldn't have to waste time and he could spend his time during
the day in the בית המדרש Beis Medrash and doing the learning.
Okay so that's what so that's so so that's why he mentions
specifically חול המועד Chol haMoed and it's according to this it wasn't
an issue of not cheating people and having the exact amount but
it was the issue of just not wasting time during the day.
It sounds also that this is that it's saying that the אבא
שאול Abba Shaul of the משנה mishnah, who who said the second
statement אף במועד עושה כן af b'mo'ed oseh kein is the same
as the אבא שאול בן בטנית. Abba Shaul ben Botnit. I don't
know I didn't get a chance to look it up but it
seems reasonable that the that we're saying it's the same one. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan
our Rabbis taught הוא כנס שלוש מאות גרבי יין מדירוי המדה. hu
kanas shalosh me'os garvei yayin mideirui hamiddah. And now we're going to
see that there is an issue here not just about having time
to learn on יום טוב Yom Tov but also not cheating people.
It says what he would do is he would after he gave
measured out for people the wine you know there would be a
little bit that would be the difference like again if I pour
you a if I have a like if I pour into your
vessel and your vessel like has marks let's say at the one
liter mark and I pour wine into your vessel it's going to
hit the one liter mark right now but if we wait five
minutes for it to settle it'll be a little bit less. Okay
but normally in the business nobody has that time we're not waiting
five minutes presumably you're מוחל mocheil you know you fill it up
you know of course when you all get I don't know about
you me when I go to get soda at the you know
from the fountain right at the movie theater whatever it is you
know you know you wait give it a minute to settle and
fill it up some more right but but anyway here presumably it
wasn't I mean although the wine's a lot more expensive than soda
but anyway presumably it wasn't that big of a difference and people
wouldn't want to wait so it would be understood they would be
מוחל mocheil but I would fill up your thing and and in
the end there'd be extra left over in my vessel because I
hadn't really fully filled it up because it looked like it was
full but it wasn't full. And by the end of the year
he had collected again this is an exaggeration
300 barrels of wine or whatever 300 flasks of wine from the
leftover wine that people you know that that he did not fill
up of people's measure. It's sort of like you know the whole
issue about the rounding error in banks you know somebody you know
what happens when the bank figures out your interest and it's less
than a penny who gets that less than a penny so the
bank would always keep it for for themselves and then somebody this
was a whole story whatever somebody a computer programmer who was working
for the banks basically found a way to funnel that money into
like his own Swiss bank account you know and everybody every person's
little half penny over every time the bank computed the interest turned
into millions of dollars. Okay so that's what happened here. Everybody's little
half penny that he didn't fill up the exact amount in the
end it was 300 barrels or flasks worth of wine again there's
probably an exaggeration but let's take a look at how it goes
on. וחביריו כנסו שלוש מאות גרבי שמן ממיצוי המדה. V'chaveirav kinsu shalosh
me'os garvei shemen mimitzuy hamiddah. And as I said the other problem
is if you're giving oil you pour it out but like you'd
have to wait all like hours for all the oil to come
out of the measuring vessel. So I have an exact liter of
oil here I'm going to pour it into your vessel we're not
going to sit around waiting all day for it all to come
out. Okay so there's going to be some that I'm going to
keep to myself at the end. And by the end of a
year or a few years there was 300 you know flasks of
oil left over that I had because I didn't give it to
the people you know technically really was deserving to them. So what
did they do with this? They felt guilty about it. So they
rather than moving it into a Swiss bank account what did they
do? הביאום לפני הגזברים לירושלים Hevi'um lifnei hagizbarim l'Yerushalayim they brought it
to the officers of the Temple in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואמרו להם V'amru
lahem they said so the so they wanted to give it you
know give it away they didn't want to keep it to themselves.
אמרו להם Amru lahem so these officers you know the treasurers said
to them אי אתם זקוקים לכך ee atem zkukim l'kach yeah you're
being very פרום frum but there's no need like people are מוחל
mocheil it's all understood. אמרו להם Amru lahem so they said back
to the treasurers אף אנו אין רצוננו בכך af anu ein retzonenu
b'kach it's very nice what you say we're not we're not responsible
but we don't want to keep it. It's it doesn't belong to
us. אמרו להם הואיל והחמרתם על עצמכם Amru lahem ho'il v'hichmartem al
atzmechem that's a very funny interesting that phrase החמרתם על עצמכם hichmartem
al atzmechem I don't know how often that occurs in חז"ל. Chazal.
Since you're being stringent on Since you're being stringent on yourselves, אתם
יהיו מאות של רבים. Atem yiheyu maot shel rabbim. You shouldn't use
this for the temple. Don't, you know, it's not all give it
to צדקה. tzedakah. That's, I did the thing wrong, I'll give it
to צדקה. tzedakah. It's not about צדקה, tzedakah, it's about giving it
back to the people. So you're not obligated, but if you want
to give it back to the people, find a way to give
back to the people, not to give it to the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. דתניא, D'tanya, we saw in a ברייתא, braita, גזל ואינו
יודע למי גזל. gezel v'eino yodea l'mi gazal. Nobody's saying they stole
here, but this is being used as the model. If somebody stole
and he doesn't know who he stole from, don't say, oh, I'll
just give it to צדקה. tzedakah. Why? Because צדקה tzedakah isn't the
person you stole from. So יעשם בצרכי רבים. Ya'asem b'tzorchei rabbim. You
should use the money for communal goods, communal purposes, so ultimately you'll
be benefiting some of the people that you took it from. מאי
ניהו? Mai nihu? What is that? אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda,
בורות שיחין ומערות. borot shichin u'mearot. You dig wells. Everybody needs good
water wells, so use the money towards the digging of wells. Okay,
so that's what they said, you should give this money to some
communal purpose and don't give it towards the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
if you're feeling guilty about it, then do something more appropriate with
it. Dov, you had a question before?
Yeah, two short things. One is it's really common when you go
like in a שוק shuk and you buy something in bulk, the
guy measures it out to you, and he takes a little extra
scoop and he throws it in. Because of that. Yeah, yeah. Also,
is there the phrase
בנות ישראל החמירו על עצמן?
Bnot
Yisrael hechemiru al atzman? Similar, right? Right, so that is החמרתם על
עצמכם hechmartem al atzmechem and החמירו על עצמן. hechemiru al atzman. Right,
comes, does come up in נידה. Niddah. Thank you. Yes, it does
come up there as well. Correct. Okay, so now the גמרא goes
on. אדבריה רב חסדא לרבנא עוקבא Adbarya Rav Chisda l'Rabana Ukva ודרש,
v'darash, and he expounded, meaning he presumably used Rabana Ukva as his
loudspeaker, and he expounded. לא ימדוד אדם שעורים ויתן לפני בהמתו ביום
טוב. Lo yimdod adam se'orim v'yiten lifnei behemto b'Yom Tov. Now we're
back to יום טוב Yom Tov. concerns, measuring. So the same way
you can't measure in general on שבת and יום טוב, Yom Tov,
and certainly there's even more problems when you're borrowing it from a
friend because then it's more like transaction. So now we're going to
talk about measuring out your dog food or your food for your
animal. Is that also a problem of measuring? He says, yes, it
is! You're still measuring. So again, remember two problems of measuring. One
is in a transactionary context where it's more problematic, and the other
is to do it even by yourself, and there's a prohibition of
מדידה medidah because it relates to business even between you and
yourself. לא ימדוד אדם שעורים ויתן לפני בהמתו, Lo yimdod adam se'orim
v'yiten lifnei behemto, don't measure out an exact amount of barley and
give it to your animal ביום טוב. b'Yom Tov. אבל קודר הוא
קב וקביין ונותן לפני בהמתו. Aval koder hu kav v'kavayim v'noten lifnei
behemto. But what you can do is you can scoop out a
קב kav or two קביין kavayim and give it. ואינו חושש. V'eino
choshesh. So what's the difference? So רש"י Rashi basically says the difference
here is
that the question is that are you basically, you know, it's one
thing that you use a measuring vessel and then you pour into
something else? Like, this is the box I'm going to give my
animal to, and I scoop out a particular amount and I pour
into it. Then I'm like measuring, using this to measure, right? Because
then I'm using it to measure and then I'm putting it in
the container that I'm going to give to my animal. But if
you scoop out, it's sort of like using the cup and going
and saying, can you fill this up for me like we had
before? Right? If you use the thing itself to convey the thing
to the animal and to present it to the animal and you're
scooping out with the thing itself and you're not pouring it into
something else, that would be okay. All right, so let's take a
look. ואינו
חושש. V'eino choshesh. והנחתום, V'hanachtom, a baker, מודד תבלין ונותן לתוך קדרתו.
moded tavlin v'noten l'toch kderato. So now it's fascinating, some people we
actually do give an allowance to measure because anybody who knows, you
know, cooking is a much more inexact type of a practice than
baking. Baking, the measurements have to be extremely precise. And also, I
was just, you know, they want you to use weights and not
volume because weighing things is much more precise. So if you have
a נחתום, nachtom, they actually allowed him to measure out the spices
כדי שלא יקדיח תבשילו, kdei shelo yakdiach tavshilo, in order that his,
now it's funny though, because it says קדרה kdera and תבשיל tavshil
which has to do more with a stew than it has to
do with a נחתום, nachtom, however, is a baker. So I don't
exactly get, and תבלין tavlin is more that's used for a stew.
But anyway, somebody that is a professional cook, they did allow a
certain amount of measuring of the spices, which raises a question. So
does that mean if I'm making something at home on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, I can measure out a teaspoon, a tablespoon? Is that
part of the איסור מדידה issur medidah or not part? Who falls
into the category here of נחתום? nachtom? Not very clear. From here
it sounds like it's only in a professional context. Okay. רש"י Rashi
says מבשל קדרה נמי קרי נחתום. mevashel kdera nami kari nachtom. נחתום
Nachtom is not only a baker, it's even somebody that's making it,
but it still sounds that somebody is in a professional context. So
not exactly clear what the degree of allowance is. אמר רבי ירמיה
בר אבא אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah bar Abba amar Rav, מודדת
אשה קמח ביום טוב ונותנת לתוך עיסתה modedet isha kemach b'Yom Tov
v'notenet l'toch issatah כדי שתטול חלה בעין יפה. kdei shetitol challah b'ayin
yafa. That a woman can measure the exact amount of flour on
יום טוב Yom Tov. that she's using to make her dough so
that when she separates out חלה, challah, she separates out a generous
amount. If she doesn't know exactly how much flour she has, she'll
be a little bit more stingy. If she knows exact, then she
won't play it safe and she'll give the appropriate amount. ושמואל. U'Shmuel.
ושמואל אמר אסור U’Shmuel amar assur שמואל Shmuel says, I'm sorry, that's
not measuring for the sake of the food directly, that's measuring for
the sake of חלה, Challah, of separating חלה, Challah, and I'm not
going to allow you to measure for that purpose. והתנא דבי שמואל
מותר, V’ha tana d’vei Shmuel mutar, one minute, how could שמואל Shmuel
say it's forbidden? There's a ברייתא braita taught from the ישיבה yeshiva
of שמואל Shmuel that says it's permissible. אמר אביי השתא דאמר שמואל
אסור, Amar Abaye hashta d’amar Shmuel assur, שמואל Shmuel himself says forbidden,
ותנא דבי שמואל מותר, v’tana d’vei Shmuel mutar, but the ברייתא braita
from the house of שמואל Shmuel says it's permissible to measure out
the exact amount of flour to separate
חלה. Challah. הלכה למעשה שמואל הלכה למעשה אסור לאשמעינן, Halacha l'maaseh Shmuel
halacha l'maaseh assur l'ashmiunan, שמואל Shmuel is telling us the bottom line
הלכה, halacha, not necessarily the theoretical הלכה. halacha. And רש"י Rashi says
here it's another example of הלכה ואין מורין כן, halacha v’ein morin
kein, that in theory the הלכה halacha is that it's מותר mutar
to measure out flour for the sake of knowing exactly how to
separate חלה, Challah, but in practice שמואל Shmuel would prefer that people
not do it. Okay, one of these other differences between the theoretical
הלכה halacha and the practical הלכה. halacha. And then there's a whole
question: how do we פוסק? pasken? Do we פוסק pasken like שמואל?
Shmuel? Do we פוסק pasken like רב? Rav? Are you allowed to
measure out flour? And I should say תוספות Tosafot has an interesting
discussion because תוספות Tosafot says we don't separate now like a certain
amount of flour to give to the כהן, Kohen, we separate out
it's only symbolic and we burn it, so there shouldn't be an
allowance to know exactly how much because it's not going to affect
the size that you separate out. Except, says תוספות, Tosafot, we do
have to know how much flour we're using. Why do we have
to know how much flour you're using for a חלה Challah purpose?
Not to determine how much חלה Challah to separate but to determine
whether you need to separate חלה Challah and say, okay, we'll just
separate with a ספק, safek, but do I make a ברכה bracha
or not? So תוספות Tosafot has a discussion: can you measure the
exact amount of flour so that you'll know whether or not you
have to make a ברכה bracha rather than not making a ברכה
bracha because you're playing it safe? And in the end he says,
no, just be either overly generous so you have no doubt that
you're obligated with a ברכה, bracha, or make it clearly in smaller
quantities so you have no doubt that you're exempt. But he has
a similar question about measuring flour to determine whether you can make
a ברכה. bracha. But the more, the bigger question I would say
for us is the case of the cook, of the chef, and
are we allowed to like use tablespoons and teaspoons on יום טוב
Yom Tov, in our own cooking?
Yes, sorry, what was the case of שלא יקדיח תבשיל? shelo yakdiach
tavshil?
יקדיח yakdiach means like spoil, but it could mean burn, but it
doesn't literally mean burn, it means like over-spice so it's inedible. Okay,
so it means ruin, okay, ruin.
If you make it too spicy? Yeah, exactly.
Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: אין שונין קמח ביום
טוב, Ein shonin kemach b’Yom Tov, you cannot double-sift flour on יום
טוב. Yom Tov, If it's already been sifted, you can't sift it
again. Now again, sifting is normally one of those things that goes
takes place out in the field or in the pre-processing stage, but
maybe, you know, some people even after they bring flour home they
want to sift it again to make it extra pure, so maybe
it's allowed because it's more like this kitchen-based type of a thing.
So the גמרא says it's not
allowed. משום רבי פפי ורבי יהודה בן בתירא אמרו שונין, Mishum Rabbi
Papi v’Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira amru shonin, yes, you can re-sift your
flour on יום טוב, Yom Tov. ושוין, v’shavin, and everybody agrees שנפל
לתוכו צרור או קיסם, shenafal l’tocho tzeror o kismam, that if it
actually became impure, like a rock or a little, you know, piece
of wood fell into it, a chip of wood, ששונין, sheshonin, that
then you could re-sift it. Okay, תני תנא קמיה דרבינא, Tani tana
kamei d’Ravina, a תנא tana prodded in the presence of רבינא: Ravina:
אין שונין קמח ביום טוב, Ein shonin kemach b’Yom Tov, you cannot
re-sift your flour, אבל נפל צרור או קיסם בורר בידו, aval nafal
tzeror o kismam borer b’yado, but if a little piece of wood
or a rock fell into it, then don't re-sift it, but pick
it out with your hand. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back
to him, כל שכן דאסור, kol sheken d’assur, no, that makes it
worse if you pick it out with your hand, דהוי ליה כבורר,
d’havei lei k’borer, that's more like a clear act of בורר. borer.
Now of course you would say sifting, isn't that an act of
בורר? borer? I mean, sifting, the whole point is to separate it
out. So רש"י Rashi tries to figure that out, and רש"י Rashi
says
that he says visually when you sift, right, if you ever see
somebody, I mean some people in their kitchen re-sift the flour, it's
not clear that anything is being separated. Once it's already sifted flour,
you know, why is this person doing it? I don't know, maybe
it loosens it up or something, but there's not, aerates it, there's
not like a clear thing that's being bad that's being taken out.
But if you go specifically with your hand and pull it out,
that's more that it's an act of בורר. borer. Now again, בורר
borer in certain contexts is allowed in יום טוב, Yom Tov you
know, in a particular kitchen-type of a context, and we had a
whole משנה before בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
So this gets to the issue about is this like an עובדא
דחול uvda d’chol concern, or רש"י Rashi here says it's a מלאכה
melacha concern? But again, why is it a מלאכה? melacha? You know,
what exactly defines when these things are considered part of preparing food
and when does it define them as preparatory, which are not allowed?
So here the גמרא says that in some cases, when it is
necessary you can do it, but maybe not with your hand, that
makes it too obvious that you are doing בורר. borer. דרש רבא
בר רב הונא זוטא אפיתחא דנהרדעא, Darash Rava bar Rav Huna Zuti
apitcha d’Nahardea, so רבא the son of the younger רב הונא, Rav
Huna, the small רב הונא, Rav Huna, expounded by the by the
opening of נהרדעא, Nahardea, like the gates of נהרדעא, Nahardea, whatever public
square, שונין קמח ביום טוב, shonin kemach b’Yom Tov, you can re-sift
flour on יום טוב. אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman,
so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to him, פוקו ואמרו... puku v’amru...
פוקו ואמרו ליה לאבא, Puku ve'amru lei le-abba, go tell אבא abba
meaning my friend there, שקילו טיבותייך ושדי אחיזרי. Shekilo tivotayich v'shadi achaziri.
So take all of to take all of your, take your favors
and throw them on the thorns, meaning you know you think you're
being very you're wonderful you're coming to the town and you're telling
everybody you can resift your flour, who needs you? פוק חזי כמה
מהולתא הדרין בנהרדעא. Puk chazi kama mehulta hadrin bi'Narda'ah. Go look around
and see how many sifters are circulating around נהרדעא. Narda'ah. Everybody knows
it, everybody resifts their flour on יום טוב, nobody needed your big
חידוש chiddush that you come to tell us this. Okay, so here
not only before it said it's forbidden, not only is it saying
permitted here, it's saying it's like patently obvious that it's permitted. Okay,
ודביתהו דרב יוסף, u'devaytehu de'Rav Yosef, and Rav Yosef's wife, נהלא קימחא
אגבא דמהולתא. nahala kimcha agaba de'mehulta. She resifted flour on יום טוב,
but she did it with a שינוי, shinuy, she used the back
of the sifter, not the not the normal way. אמר לה, Amar
lah, so he said to her, חזי, Chazi, he said it's all
very nice you're being frum, but pay attention דאנא ריפתא מעלייתא בעינא.
de'ana rifta ma'alyata be'ina. I'd like to have nice bread. So meaning
it's very nice you're trying to be frum, do it the normal
way, I prefer that, you know, I want my bread to be
well sifted. Yeah, that is a problem. I know. And the previous
also he's been a little mean. Okay,
ודביתהו דרב אשי u'devaytehu de'Rav Ashi נהלא קימחא אגבא דפתורא. nahala kimcha
agaba de'patura. So Rav Ashi's wife sifted flour on the back of
the table, which maybe means that rather than into a normal vessel,
it not not that she used that as her sifter, but that's
what she used to catch the flour. Also doing some type of
a שינוי. shinuy. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, so Rav Ashi
said, הדידן, hadi'dan,
that of us, meaning my wife, ברתה דרמי בר חמא berateh de'Rami
bar Chama is the daughter of Rami bar Chama. ורמי בר חמא
מרא דעובדא הוה. ve'Rami bar Chama marei de'uvda hava. Rami bar Chama
was very frum. ואי לאו דחזיא מבי נשא לא הוי עבדא. ve'ei
lav de'chazya mi'bei nasha lo hava avda. If she hadn't seen this
from the woman's house, meaning her mother's house, like this is the
mimetics tradition, right, she would not have been doing it now that
she's married to me. So here it ends by giving weight and
legitimacy to saying we don't necessarily resift flour in the normal way.
So once again brings up this question of what types of things
are allowed for food if they're processes that normally take place, you
know, outside of the kitchen. Last משנה, end let's end the פרק.
perek. הולך אדם אצל חנווני הרגיל אצלו, Holech adam eitzel chanvani ha'ragil
eitzlo, you can go to a storekeeper that you are familiar with.
The reason it has to be familiar with is that he'll trust
you to pay you up after יום טוב. So before we were
talking about the butcher, your friend, now we're talking about the storekeeper.
ואומר לו, ve'omer lo, and you say to him, תן לי ביצים
ואגוזים במנין. Ten li beitzim ve'egozim be'minyan. Give me like a dozen
eggs, give me like fifty nuts. Okay, and you can mention the
number of nuts and the number of eggs. Why? שכן דרך בעל
הבית להיות מונה בתוך ביתו, she'ken derech ba'al ha'bayit li'hiyot moneh be'toch
beito,
because you don't only use number, you know, when you are doing
transactions. You know, you'll say I need three eggs for my, you
know, for this, you know, for this
cake that I'm making. You know, or I need I don't know
if you'd say fifty nuts, but whatever. But giving a number is
like is not necessarily make it more like a transaction. You know,
as opposed to weighing something and giving a weight to something or
giving like a cup's worth or three cups' worth or whatever that
makes it more transactionary. This not so much, so it can look
more like you're just borrowing it or he's giving it to you,
it doesn't necessarily look as much of a transaction. Let's take a
look. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. הולך אדם אצל רועה הרגיל
אצלו. Holech adam eitzel ro'eh ha'ragil eitzlo. You can go to a
shepherd that you're familiar with, ואומר לו תן לי גדי אחד או
טלה אחד. ve'omer lo ten li gedi echad o taleh echad. You
know, can you give me a sheep or a goat? And you
say give, but obviously you're going to pay him back. Okay, but
that's allowed, you're not it's not transactionary because again of the language
that you're using. אצל טבח הרגיל אצלו, eitzel tabach ha'ragil eitzlo, you
go to a butcher you're familiar with, ואומר לו תן לי כף
אחת או ירך אחת. ve'omer lo ten li kaf achat o yerech
achat.
Give me like one, you know, leg or give me a thigh.
And again you mention a piece, but you don't mention a weight,
and you certainly don't mention money. אצל פטם הרגיל אצלו, eitzel patam
ha'ragil eitzlo,
and you can go to a fattener, meaning somebody who fattens up
birds, ואומר לו תן לי תור אחד או גוזל אחד. ve'omer lo
ten li tor echad o gozal echad. Give me a pigeon or
give me a dove. Okay, and you just mention the number of
objects, but not a size, not a weight. אצל נחתום הרגיל אצלו,
eitzel nachtom ha'ragil eitzlo,
and by now he does mean a baker, ואומר לו תן לי
כיכר אחד. ve'omer lo ten li kikar echad. I'd like a loaf
of bread, five loaves of bread, או גלוסקא אחת, o gluska achat,
or a cake, but you don't weigh it and you and you
don't talk about money. ואצל חנווני הרגיל אצלו, ve'eitzel chanvani ha'ragil eitzlo,
or storekeeper, ואומר לו תן לי עשרים ביצים, ve'omer lo ten li
esrim beitzim, and you say give me twenty eggs, וחמישה אגוזים, va'chamisha
egozim, fifty nuts, עשרה אפרסקין, asara afar'sekin, ten,
what's an אפרסק?
afar'sek? Quince? Peaches? אפרסק Afar'sek is in modern Hebrew peaches.
Okay, וחמישה רמונים, va'chamisha rimonim, and five pomegranates, ואתרוג אחד, ve'etrog echad,
one etrog. Fascinating what this reveals about how people would use and
the quantities people would do. One אתרוג. etrog. So they would use
אתרוגים etrogim during, I mean is it is it סוכות? Sukkot? Does
the storekeeper have אתרוגים? etrogim? Is that why we're talking about it?
It is a יום טוב anyway. That you can mention all these
things, ובלבד שלא יזכיר לו סכום מידה. u'bilvad she'lo yazkir lo skum
midah. Don't just mention the exact weight. That's the way רש"י interprets
this. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer. Exactly
the exact cost of it. So don't talk about weights and cost,
but you can talk about numbers and that does not look transactionary.
OK. הדרן עלך אין צדין Hadran Alach Ein Tzadin and we're starting
tomorrow morning.